Previously on Gotham...
You're the brother I never had.
We will create a
legacy in this city.
Gotham falls,
we rise.
Together.
BARBARA: Poor Jim.
All alone again.
- I told you to leave.
- I heard you.
GORDON: So many
things I wish I could change.
Things I've done.
We're here now. We'll try to put
the pieces back together again.
BARBARA: Jim,
I'm pregnant.
- This isn't you.
- We're not the same.
That night that your
parents were murdered,
I didn't do anything,
because I didn't care.
Everyone, let's
dig a little deeper.
'Cause that's the only
way you're all making it out
of this hole.
- SELINA:
Deep enough?
- (groans)
You're leaving Gotham.
OSWALD: There's nothing
left for me here anymore.
I've done all I can.
I want in.
(grunting)
JEREMIAH: I love
family reunions.
Don't you?
(grunting)
Go. Go, go.
(indistinct shouting)
♪♪
- Which way?
- Wait.
♪♪
(whizzing)
(coughing)
(choking)
♪♪
General,
you were the ones
who let Walker operate
right under your noses.
Now you're telling me
she evaded capture?
WADE: I understand
your frustration.
Have you at least determined
why she did what she did?
Not yet.
Look, bottom line,
Walker and Dorrance
are out of the picture.
What else is standing in
the way of reunification?
WADE: Nothing.
I'm recommending we begin
the process immediately.
There have been a lot of
promises from across the river.
WADE: But unlike
Walker, or whoever she is,
I have the authority
to take action.
Unless something happens
to destabilize Gotham again,
this nightmare is about to end.
BULLOCK: Think he's for real?
I'll believe it when it happens.
I take it your search
party didn't find Alfred.
Neither hide nor hair.
Pennyworth vanished
five days ago.
It ain't looking good.
How's Bruce?
He's been pulling double
shifts on the search parties.
Kid's dead on his feet.
I want to search this area next.
There are whole blocks
of abandoned buildings.
- I'll get a squad right on it.
- Just give me five minutes.
- I'll be ready.
- No.
You're not going out.
- No, Jim...
- You need your rest.
I'm not cutting you out,
but I need you sharp,
not a liability.
I just don't understand
what could have happened.
Neither do I.
But I know that
Alfred Pennyworth
can take care of himself.
I'll send for you
if I hear anything.
Kid's tough.
Yeah.
In other good-ish
news, Harper radioed.
Her squad found something.
What?
It's weird.
- (camera shutter clicks)
- (siren whoops)
HARPER: Four men.
Looks like they breathed in
some sort of chemical agent.
I'm thinking airborne.
And the Z's on their bodies?
Carved into them
before time of death.
Check out the mustache.
- Fake.
- Seems like
they escaped from here.
GORDON: A film set?
HARPER: I said it was weird.
BULLOCK: Zs on their chests.
Think it could be Zsasz?
Chemicals aren't really his MO.
Plus, I never figured Zsasz
for much of a cinephile.
But whoever it is, if they
have more of these chemicals
and the will to use them...
It's bye-bye, reunification.
Got to stop him before
news reaches the mainland.
The Chessmen.
That's a gang that operates out
of the Narrows. What
the hell is a Narrows gang
doing way up here?
I think we both know
someone we can ask.
♪♪
(woman laughs)
(indistinct chatter)
Can you check on
the fever in Bed 12?
What's up, Doc?
Heard you were
working here. Interesting.
It's what I do, help people.
Speaking of which,
I've got patients.
Oh, you wouldn't kick
Jim's baby mama to the curb,
- now, would you?
- Whatever happened
between you
and Jim, it's none
of my concern.
So if you're here to gloat...
I'm here for medical assistance.
For my little nugget.
What do you say?
Be my O.B.?
You can't be serious.
I know we've had
our differences.
You tried to kill me, Barbara.
Twice.
That was years ago.
There are other doctors here.
Not as good as you.
Look,
whatever you
think of me, my child
is innocent, and I
want the best for it.
And in this place,
that means you.
(sighs)
Does Jim know you're here?
- This is none
of his business.
- (door opens)
GORDON: Lee?
Jim.
- Barbara.
- BARBARA:
You're interrupting.
Doctor-patient. Blow.
I'm sorry, you're her doctor?
No. I don't know.
Maybe. What are you doing here?
Some bodies turned up.
They might have a
Narrows connection.
I wouldn't have come, but...
It's important. Right.
You two need to
talk. I'll be outside.
- Uh, I'd rather not.
- If you want me
to be your doctor,
you will talk to
the baby's... father.
Your first appointment is next
week. The nurse will give you
all your vitamins
when you leave.
Deal?
Is she really the only
one you could find?
She's the best doctor
in this hellhole of a city.
Not everything is
about Jim Gordon.
Pretty sure this one is.
Because we slept together. Yeah.
I only told you because I
felt you had a right to know.
But your involvement
in this ended
the moment you put
your pants back on.
(scoffs)
What?
You don't think I'm
fit to be a mother?
What do you think?
Barbara.
(door opens forcefully)
(rats squeaking)
(woman laughing)
(clinking)
(laughing continues)
(speaks inaudibly)
(giggles)
Who are you?
Well, look who
decided to join us.
Hello, champ.
ALFRED: Master Bruce!
Alfred, how did you...
Look at the state of you.
What have I told you about
rolling around in the muck?
Alfred, what's going on?
Who are these people?
MAN: Whatever do
you mean, Bruce?
We're your parents.
Right. Well, let's
get you spruced up.
After all,
we have a guest.
Welcome home, Bruce.
Jeremiah. You're alive.
(laughs) Well, you
didn't think Selina
could kill me so
easily, did you?
(laughs) I just had to
put you off my scent
until I could
finalize my... project.
Manners, Master Bruce.
Let's not be rude to our guest.
Especially when I
come bearing gifts.
ALFRED: Oh,
Mr. Jeremiah. A cake.
How exceedingly kind of you.
Is it Italian meringue?
Sure.
Oh.
Now, now, Bruce, you come
any closer and I
blow up Wayne Manor,
with all of us inside of it.
I have a dozen
more of these, uh,
Italian meringues sprinkled
all throughout the house.
What did you do to Alfred?
And who are these people?
Ah, glad you asked.
Mm, come.
(quietly): Come, come.
JEREMIAH: Mommy
and Daddy dearest
were just an innocent
couple I kidnapped based on...
bone structure and, um...
build.
Just a touch
of plastic surgery, and voilà...
Waynes.
(chuckles)
Alfred I nabbed
in the Green Zone.
They're hypnotized.
Well, I'm afraid
there was no room
for improv in our script.
Today is a...
very important day, Bruce.
Just look at the
way they're dressed.
It's the night my
parents were killed.
And I'm giving you the chance
to experience it all over again.
Why?
Isn't it obvious?
Bruce...
this...
this was the most
important day of your life.
And I didn't get
to be a part of it.
We need to rectify that.
Alfred. It's time for dinner.
Chop-chop. We're on
a very tight schedule.
Of course, Mr. Jeremiah.
(motor chugging)
(explosion)
That's zero for three.
Yes.
It seems the government
was quite thorough
- when they mined
the river.
- You didn't have a plan
to get off this rock before
you stole everyone's crap?
I was working on a plan.
The river is mined.
Everything that flies out
gets blown from... the...
- sky.
- What?
Jeremiah was digging
a tunnel under the river.
A tunnel?
(chuckles) Really?
Do you have any better ideas?
Didn't think so.
It's in the Dark Zone.
We should wait until
night to check it out.
Well, I was running out
of guinea pigs anyway.
Oh, look!
He's swimming to shore.
(explosion)
THOMPKINS: Are you sure
you should be out
in the Narrows alone?
When the bridges fell, this
place descended into chaos.
Figure our best bet of
getting out in one piece is
- to keep a low profile.
- So all the work I did
to make the Narrows better
- was for nothing.
- (loud clattering)
(indistinct shouts,
man whistles)
It's the Leopards.
Rivals of the Chessmen.
(men speaking indistinctly)
About this Barbara thing...
Uh, Jim, just don't.
No, it's important to
me that you understand.
(sighs)
Okay. So, what are you gonna do?
I don't know, but
it's my child, too.
Barbara seems to have
a difference of opinion.
But hey, people change.
You don't know her like I do.
You can say that again.
(engine revs, pulls away)
Look.
We're clear.
The Chessmen moved around.
They used these as
signals for their members.
The rook's a compass needle.
North-northeast. Let's go.
♪♪
Hmm.
Alfred told me
such great tidbits
about your childhood.
How you used to eat here,
in the kitchen, when it
was just you and the family.
My, how...
homey and intimate.
Grilled cheese and Branston
pickle sandwich, Mr. Jeremiah.
Master Bruce's favorite.
My influence, though
Thomas did add a dash
of aioli for extra flair.
(laughing)
Oh. Come on, Bruce.
That's a weird favorite
food for a 12-year-old.
I'm playing your game.
Now let Alfred and
these people go.
They're innocent.
I'm sorry, Bruce, it's just...
it's very important
to me that I get
every detail exactly right.
Speaking of which...
the final touch.
♪♪
What was it like...
losing your parents that night?
(deep, distorted gunshot)
I lost my family, too, Bruce.
The wound still hasn't healed.
I... think about it often.
None of this is real.
You're trying to manipulate me.
It will never be real.
But you are thinking
about that night.
That's all I need.
I just want to be
connected to you.
I offered for you to
be my best friend!
But I've realized if we...
can't be friends...
then we can be
connected in other ways.
How?
You'll see.
In time.
Hmm.
I'm sorry to cut
tonight short...
but...
your parents and I have
a very important date...
Jeremiah.
- With destiny.
- Jeremiah!
You might want to find
your faithful butler and leave.
Quickly.
(steady beeping)
Alfred!
(bell tolling)
The signs lead this way.
Look at the smoke.
Someone restarted production.
(tanks burbling)
My God, Jim...
look at all of this.
Come on.
- Who's in charge here?
- (softly):
Tick tock,
the chemical stock,
shall give our
Gotham an aftershock.
Tick tock, the chemical stock,
shall give our
Gotham an aftershock.
Tick tock, the chemical stock...
shall give our
Gotham an aftershock.
They've been hypnotized.
Tetch.
- (one person clapping)
- WORKERS:
Tick tock,
the chemical stock
shall give our
Gotham an aftershock.
My, my, what a thrill.
Jim Gordon...
and the woman
he told me to kill.
(mock gasp) Brings
back memories.
That tea party, so long ago.
But now, to order these
men to attack my foe!
(Thompkins yelps)
JERVIS: All for
one, and one for all!
Ain't this a grand old ball!
(grunts)
(pipes clanging)
Yoo-hoo!
(gasps) Jim!
Ain't this...
some... game!
Give it to me again?
(sighs) Penguin
has been stealing
everything in the city
that's not nailed down,
and now he needs a way
of getting it off the island.
Hmm. And you're helping him?
Well, that's what he thinks.
Barbara, Tabitha
was my friend, too.
If anything, I want
to gut the twerp...
- and take his loot.
- Except you don't
actually have
- a way out of Gotham.
- I'll find one tonight.
I'll still need your
help moving the stuff.
We can get out of here together.
Away from Jim Gordon.
Rich as Midas.
Penguin dead in a ditch.
Well, aren't we just two
single ladies and a baby
about to kill our
sworn enemy together.
What?
It's just you're pregnant.
Don't even start.
BRUCE (in distance): Alfred!
(beeping)
(in distance): Alfred!
(running footsteps)
- (beeping)
- Alfred. We need
to get out of here.
Ah, Master Bruce. I was
just taking a quiet moment
- to tidy up.
- We need to go.
- The bombs.
- What bombs?
These bombs.
No need for roughhousing, sir.
(beeping continues)
There has to be a way.
Alfred, you'd do anything
to protect me, right?
- Absolutely, sir.
- There's a gas leak. In the kitchen.
It's only a matter of time
before this whole place goes up.
A gas leak? Where
are your parents?
- Where's our guest?
- I've already warned them.
I know a way out. Come on!
(rapid beeping)
(deep rumbling)
BRUCE: Alfred!
Alfred.
(groans)
Oh, bloody hell.
Don't move.
Do you, uh...?
Oh, yeah, I remember everything.
Clear as day.
And let me tell
you, if ever I see
that Jervis Tetch character
again I'll stick that watch
so far up his... his nose.
How about you?
You all right?
Yeah, I'm all right.
But the manor...
Don't you worry
about that now, son.
Come on. Help me up.
(grunts, groans)
Oh, your leg's hurt.
Yes, but it's not broken.
(grunts)
I thought I lost you.
Me?
Never, Master Bruce.
Go on.
You know where he's gonna be at.
Go.
If you're here,
Jeremiah must still be alive.
And if you're here, I'm guessing
you found our test subjects,
all boiled and
bubbled. (giggles)
What's he planning?
Shh. It's a surprise,
don't you know?
A real killer.
JERVIS: Shall I
hypnotize our friends here,
and have them slit
each other's necks?
ECCO: (laughs) Nix.
Better check with the boss.
He might have other ideas.
I'm sorry I got you
involved in this.
Don't be.
I knew what I was
getting myself into.
I know, but, Lee...
Jim, whatever
you want to tell me,
save it till we're out of here.
Fair enough.
We need to find out
what Valeska's planning.
Hey, Tetch.
You know, it's funny.
I never figured you for
Jeremiah's errand boy.
Oh, Captain. No
errands do I run.
This is simply a way
for me to have some fun.
THOMPKINS: (laughs)
Tell yourself that.
What are you when
you would take away
your games and your rhymes?
Nothing but a second-rater
with a really silly hat.
Shut up.
(whispering)
- (laughs)
- Beautiful.
Beautiful.
Lee Thompkins,
you do intrigue me so.
First, you were a doctor,
then the Narrows queen.
Tell me, please do,
are you running from your past
when you become someone new?
(door creaks)
When I found Jeremiah,
he had a bunch of crazies
digging this tunnel for him.
Well, that certainly
fills me with confidence.
- Whoa. You hear that?
- (rustling nearby)
(footsteps approaching)
- Alfred.
- Selina.
What are you doing here?
And with that?
I should ask you the same thing.
What's down that tunnel?
Well, it was Wayne Manor
till Jeremiah blew it up.
He sealed the only
way out of Gotham.
SELINA: No.
J-Jeremiah is not alive.
I-I saw him die right here.
Yeah, well, you're wrong.
We all were.
And now he's embarked
on some madcap scheme
where he's reenacting the
night Bruce's parents were killed.
Where's Bruce?
ALFRED: He's
gone after Jeremiah.
He could use your help.
Wait.
Don't you think that because
I did not kill Jeremiah does
not mean that I won't kill you.
Selina.
You killed my friend Tabitha.
- You deserve to die.
- (grunts)
Selina.
Just put the knife down.
Bruce needs you.
(gasping)
I suppose I should thank you.
Or you could help
me to the Green Zone.
Of course. It's that way.
Jeremiah!
Show yourself!
(dramatic film score playing)
♪♪
Olé!
Hola, Bruce.
Well, here we are,
the theater where your mommy
and daddy took you to see
The Mark of Zorro.
Ha-ha!
I had heard you were
obsessed with this man as a child.
I wonder what it was
that intrigued you so?
Was it the fact
that he struck fear
into the hearts of his enemy?
♪♪
En garde!
Hee-yah!
Take that, you villain.
Vagabond.
(screaming)
- Scoundrel.
- (screaming)
- (grunting)
- (laughing)
- (screaming)
(dramatic music ends)
Warned you.
Perhaps the movie
was a bit too effective.
Isn't this the part where
you became frightened?
When you asked
your parents to leave?
I wonder what
would have happened
if you hadn't done that.
If you had conquered your fear.
Maybe your parents
would still be alive.
♪♪
Well, on to the last
and final stop down memory lane.
(filmstrip clicking)
Stop!
That's far enough, Bruce.
BRUCE: Jeremiah.
You don't have to do this.
But I...
I do.
You see, I-I came
to this realization.
I realized that no
matter what I did
to bond us, some
random gunman in an alley
would be the man who
you were tied to the most.
The man you saw when
you closed your eyes.
I want to be the
star of the show.
So if I can't have you as
a brother bonded by love,
then we'll just have to
be bonded by hatred.
BRUCE: And you
think killing two people
that look like my
parents will do that?
It won't.
Well, then it's a good
thing I already put
a bullet in both of
their fraudulent skulls.
Oh, you're confused.
You're wondering if
I already shot them,
then who's this lovely couple?
Thomas, Martha...
why don't you turn around?
- Jim!
- (Jeremiah laughs)
I know.
See, o-over the course
of our little adventure,
fate brought to me James
Gordon and Leslie Thompkins,
and I thought to
myself, why not...
why not kill the
man who you think of
as your second father figure?
And your dear, dear,
dear friend Lee Thompkins.
And when I do,
finally, you and I will
be bound together.
Because you see...
("La Cucaracha" plays)
re-unification with the
mainland hangs on by a thread.
Those fireworks go off
and toxic chemicals
rain down onto the city,
and the government...
(clicks tongue)
cuts us adrift for good.
BRUCE: Jeremiah.
Don't.
Shh.
The pièce de résistance.
One last thing.
I had Jervis Tetch
hypnotize them
so that they'll wake
up the moment
these beautiful
pearls hit the ground.
I want you to see them
realize what I've done to them
as the life drains
from their bodies.
Never forget,
this is all for you, Bruce.
No!
Selina! The pearls!
Ecco! Now!
(timer beeping)
We need to stop the fireworks.
- They're gonna...
- I know.
You go after Jeremiah
and Ecco. I'll take the truck!
There's no way to stop them all.
Get to Harvey.
Warn the people in the
Green Zone to get to cover.
What are you... Jim!
Jeremiah!
Face me!
Here, Bruce.
(beeping rapidly)
Jeremiah!
This ends.
- Tonight.
- No.
No, Bruce. Now it begins.
(laughs)
(groans)
Yes.
You feel it. The
connection between us.
You do.
Don't you? Bruce, you feel it.
Tell me you feel it.
(groans)
You mean nothing to me.
Why don't you understand?
You need me.
I'm the answer to
your life's question!
Without me,
you're just a joke...
without a punch line.
♪♪
After all this time,
you've come to me for help.
After allowing Strange
to put a chip into my brain.
Attempting to sell
me out to Gordon.
And after naming...
a dog after me.
First of all,
I am very fond of that dog.
Secondly, I had Hugo
Strange save your life.
Thirdly, do you really think
I didn't have plans
to save you from Jim Gordon?
(chuckles)
You always have an answer
for everything, don't you, Oswald?
We have been through
all of this before.
I've tried to kill you.
You've tried to kill me.
But here we are in this room.
Together.
It means fate has
different plans for us.
What are these plans?
Haven't you realized
what Gotham is yet?
It is no longer a city.
It is a prison.
And I think it's
time we escaped.
You heard the news?
Everybody's talking about it.
Reunification isn't happening.
Word of the chemical
spill reached the mainland.
No action until the government
can determine if Gotham is safe.
I figure at least a
couple of months.
You don't sound surprised.
Guess I'm not.
Could've been much worse.
- You stopped that.
- (sighs)
Every time I think we're
turning things around,
I look up... Right
back where we started.
What were you about to say to me
when, uh, Tetch had us?
I don't know.
I guess I, uh,
would have said...
what I said the last
time we saw each other.
I wish I could go back.
Do things differently.
Better.
- It feels like a long time ago.
- Nothing's changed.
But it has, Jim.
That was a mistake.
A mistake?
Put yourself in my shoes.
After everything you said,
suddenly you're having a
baby with Barbara, of all people.
But it's not just that.
You talk about doing
things differently
and I keep thinking,
what if we hadn't lost ours?
What are you doing here, Lee?
I don't know.
I know you've taken
on so much, and...
and I want to be
understanding, but...
you let me down, Jim.
I'm sorry.
- What does that mean?
- (sighs)
For us?
I don't know.
Can't change the past,
so I guess we just
have to live with it.
No, Lee...
(monitor beeping steadily)
SELINA: I can't
believe he's still alive.
They've been doing scans,
and he has no brain activity.
He's no longer a threat.
To either of us.
Thank you for coming to help me.
That night your
parents were killed,
I should have done something.
Selina, you've done enough.
(thunder rumbles)
It's not much, but it's home.
I've been looking through
your treasure trove.
- You've been a very naughty boy.
- Barbara?
How did you...
Selina?
Hmm. She and I were
gonna go murder-halfsies
to get you back for Tabitha,
but it seems I will have
to do the dirty work myself,
as usual.
NYGMA: Oh, my God.
You're pregnant.
- How could you
possibly know that?
- Look at you.
She's glowing.
You're glowing.
How very observant
of you. Adieu, Oswald.
Wait!
Come with us.
- What?
- Yes.
I killed Tabitha.
You're angry.
You want revenge.
But do you really want
to raise your child in a
toxic waste war zone?
Come with us.
Are you telling me you
found a way out of Gotham?
Ed did.
It's a submarine.
- A submarine?
- It can track
mines in the river using sonar.
So, where's this submarine?
We have to build it.
- Yeah, I'm gonna shoot you.
- (whimpers)
God.
What is happening to me?
- Perhaps...
- Shut up!
That was a rhetorical question.
(sighs)
Fine.
I won't shoot you for
the sake of my child.
- But I will never forgive you.
- Of course.
I understand.
Call me when it's done.
- So, who's the lucky father?
- Shut up!